hey guys and welcome back to a new video
and also a new playlist which is called
Android Basics with this new playlist I
want to focus on explaining the core
Android Concepts which are purely used
for Native development and this is also
not only targeted towards beginners but
also if you're already familiar with
some Android development that is also
for you since all these basic Android
Concepts such as activities the back
stack and all these kinds of things are
often only scratched on the surface but
it definitely makes sense to go into
these a bit deeper so this playlist is
not intended to make your Android
developer from nothing but rather for
those people who are new to the Android
ecosystem or just want to deepen their
knowledge but on the one hand it assumes
that you know kotlin the programming
language we use for Native Android
development and I also won't cover any
UI building here because for that I have
my separate jetpick compose playlist on
this playlist I will talk about things
like activities the life cycle the back
stack broadcast receiver Services
intense all these Android specific
things what I will leave out though are
Concepts that don't find much
application nowadays is due to Jetpack
compose so for example fragments is a
topic where you have an older video
about but I decided to not make a video
about that in this playlist because most
new Android apps nowadays just don't use
that anymore due to Jetpack compose and
in this first video I want to talk about
activities and their life cycle
so whenever you create a new Android
Studio project then you will end up with
something like this you will have a
class main activity which is in this
case a component activity and another
studio will generate an oncreate
function which you override here with
some initial content in this case with
jetpack compose we want to ignore this
Java composter here completely and focus
on this outer thing this activity and
what that actually is an activity itself
is kind of a container for one or
multiple screens in your app but that's
only part of the truth I wouldn't only
see it as a container for screens but
rather as a unit of your app where your
users interact with and that is also why
activities are called activities and not
something like screen container so this
activity will contain information about
if it's currently active on the screen
if it's in the background it will also
serve as an entry point for your app so
that means if a user comes to your app
from another app for example your
browser um if they click on a link or so
which opens you Europe then an activity
is a component that directly gets
launched from that action and in the
past we usually did it that way that we
had one activity per screen when things
changed a bit and we got fragments so we
often bundled the different related
screens into one activity so you might
have one profile activity with a normal
profile screen a profile edit screen so
multiple screens are just bundled into
one activity which hosts these different
screens and then nowadays we got Japan
composed which usually means we will
only have a single activity in our whole
app so in this case with the jetpack
compose setup here we can have lots of
screens as many as we want while staying
in the single main activity so in pure
Japan composed products this main
activity will just serve as the entry
point for our application so if another
component another app for example a
system component needs to launch our app
then it needs to directly say I want to
launch this activity or I want to just
launch this app and this is the starting
activity of that but the main
characteristic of activities in Android
is the so-called lifecycle so that means
at some point our activity is born so
it's called created and that is what
this oncreate function stands for and at
some point it's not needed anymore all
its memory resources are freed up and
it's destroyed and in between there are
just some steps that happen which move
this activity into different so-called
lifecycle States if you just take a look
at the official activity lifecycle
diagram from the Android documentation
we get to see this picture this is the
whole lifecycle looks super complex but
let's break it down because once you
understand it it's actually fairly
simple as we already saw once the
activity is created on creators call so
it will move into the created lifecycle
State and that is just the place where
we want to initialize our variables
inside of that activity where we want to
set the actual views so the actual UI
content of that activity and just do
some further initialization at this
point the user does not see anything on
the screen yet after the created state
it will start to move into the style
started state so onstart will be called
when that is complete an activity is
considered to be startled when it
becomes visible for the user but at this
point the user still can't interact with
it yet so you can kind of compare this
with a theater where the curtains open
up initially and you can already see all
the actors and everything from the play
but the play itself is not starting yet
however after the starter state it will
move into the resume State when an
activity is in the resume state that
means it's in the foreground the user
can interact with it that's also where
it will stay until the user eventually
moves away so you can see here the
activity is running in this case so it
will block the state until something is
happening as you can see as soon as
another activity comes into the
foreground the life cycle state will
move to on pause and this is actually a
bit inaccurate because it's not only
moving to the pause State when another
activity comes into the foreground but
when any different piece of UI comes
into the foreground for example a dialog
which doesn't need to be an activity so
at this point all the resources the
activity needs will still be kept in
memory because the user might still come
back to the activity which is very
likely if they see a dialogue or so but
they just need to apply some kind of
action but it could also be that they
just navigate through different screen
of their app where they might decide to
click the back button and come back to
the previous activity and if that
happens so if the actual activity which
is in the power State comes back into
the foreground then you can see when the
user returns to the activity the
lifecycle will move back to the resume
state so it's in the foreground just as
before and it will stay there until the
user moves away again but how do we now
get from on pause to on stop you can see
the activity is no longer visible but
isn't this the same as moving away well
if the user navigates from one activity
to another activity then on stop will
also be called and the lifecycle state
will move to the stop state so what's
done the difference between the stop
State and the pause state if an activity
is in the stop State you can be sure
that it's not visible to the user
anymore if it's in the past there it
could still be that the user is seeing a
dialogue and the actual activity that is
paused is still somehow in the
background so you can imagine just like
on your desktop PC where you have
different windows so different
activities and your browser might be in
the background and you might have a
smaller window in the foreground which
is your focus so in that case the
browser which is in the background and
not focused would be in the past State
while the smaller window that is in the
foreground is in the resume State since
it has the user's Focus but as soon as
the whole window is not visible anymore
it would be considered stopped so that
would be the case if the user navigates
to another screen since then only that
new screen is visible on the screen and
not the previous screen anymore if the
user then comes back when the activity
is in the stopped State you can see then
on restart this call which is kind of a
special function when the user comes
back to an app that was minimized before
and that was hidden so this just gives
you another callback to react to exactly
this kind of use case and after that
onstart will be called again so the
activity will be made visible to the
user and then on resume where the user
can finally interact with it again but
last but not least as you saw we also
have on Destroy so what does need to
happen that our activity really gets
destroyed and all its resources get
freed up so this diagram says the
activity is finishing or being destroyed
by the system what does finishing really
mean so usually that either means that
you either intentionally closed it with
the Finish function inside of an
activity or the user is currently on
that activity and is active and then
they click the back button because that
tells the Android system a I don't want
to be active on this activity anymore
please take me to the previous one so
the current activity is not needed
anymore and it will be destroyed or
obviously as this description here says
if the system so the actual Android
operating system needs memory and it
might decide to kill your app than on
Destroy will also be invoked there's
also another special case in which the
lifecycle will reach the destroyed State
and that our so-called configuration
changes that means when some kind of
global configuration changes the most
common example is a screen rotation so
when the user rotates the device that
means the layout the activity is showing
also needs to be re-inflated it again
needs to be loaded from the resources
maybe or maybe there's a specific
landscape layout so everything will be
set up from the very beginning again and
in that case the whole activity will be
recreated and the lifecycle will start
from oncreate again as soon as the
device is in landscape mode then that
doesn't only happen with screen
rotations but also for example when
switching the language of the device and
many more but I don't want to go that
deep into these configuration changes in
this video I will talk about that in
another one but they come with more
problems than you might think at first
and if we now take a look back here in
code then for all of these lifecycle
States we have a function inside of an
activity we can override to react to
this so if we take a look here we can
also override on start which is called
as soon as the activity becomes
invisible as I said so here we could
simply print some thing
um let's say on start after on start we
would call on resume which is called as
soon as the user can interact with the
activity so here we say print line
on resume
we want to have one for one pause
print line on pause
and let's have one for on stop
print line on stop
one for destroy here we want to print
something
and what is the missing we're missing on
restart
which is called when the user comes back
to the app which was previously in the
background so here we say print line on
restart and let's also add such a log in
on create since we're missing that right
now and if we then change this to
uncreate and then launch this app on our
emulator and then also take a look in a
logcat to see our logs let's just filter
for these parentheses
or better we replace this with system
out so now we see all these functions
that get called and that is exactly what
you just saw from the diagram I showed
you initially on Creator's code when
that is done on Stardust code and when
that is done so when the activity is
visible to the user then the lifecycle
state will move in on resume and if we
take a look here on our emulator this is
currently in active activity we see the
screen we see this hello Android text so
the user is currently interacting with
the app and that is why the state stays
and resumed if we now move away so we
minimize the app for example
um completely minimize it then you will
see on pause and unstop is called on
pause because it moves into the
background and on stop because it
completely gets invisible to the user as
you can see that's the case the user
does not see anything of the activity
anymore and it's not just seeing a
dialogue or so what the activity is
still in the background and if we then
get back to the activity right here and
then you can see on restart is called
start and resume so that was exactly
what I showed you here after on stop
user comes back to the activity on
restart is called onstard is called on
resumes called and that is where it will
stay again until the user does something
moves away or closes the app let's also
quickly take a look at that when the
user closes the app by just swiping it
away
then you will see on pauses chord on
stop is called an on Destroy is called
so then the activity is really destroyed
all the resources all the UI is freed up
it's not kept in memory anymore and to
get it back on the screen we would need
to create a new one there are certain
cases where on stop and on this trial
might not be called so the Android
system does not guarantee that these are
always cold so if you have some very
important data to say for example before
the user leaves the app I would always
do that in on pause but other than that
that is how activities and the life
cycle works if you enjoyed this video
then definitely leave a subscribe and
don't miss the next Android basic videos
you'll get two new videos here every
single week Wednesday and Sunday so
definitely stay tuned I wish you an
amazing rest of your week and I'll see
you back in the next video bye bye
thank you